<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>From Scratch on OranLooney.com</title>
    <link>/tags/from-scratch/</link>
    <description>Recent content in From Scratch on OranLooney.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Copyright 2018 Oran Looney</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/from-scratch/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ML From Scratch, Part 1: Linear Regression</title>
      <link>/post/ml-from-scratch-part-1-lm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/ml-from-scratch-part-1-lm/</guid>
      <description>To kick off this series, will start with something simply yet foundational: linear regression via ordinary least squares.
Wait! don’t go yet!
We’re going to do it right, using QR decomposition. This is the same (or very close to the same) method your favorite statistical software uses under the hood, and its quite a bit more interesting than the way its usually presented to first-time students. Assuming you find linear algebra interesting, which I do, otherwise why would you be reading this?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ML From Scratch, Part 0: Introduction</title>
      <link>/post/ml-from-scratch-part-0-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/ml-from-scratch-part-0-introduction/</guid>
      <description>MotivationHow do you know if you really understand something? You could just rely on the subjective experience of feeling like you understand. This sounds plausible - surely you yourself of all people should know, right? But it runs head-first into in the (Dunning-Kruger effect)DK. A different criterion is found in this pithy quote:
“What I cannot create, I do not understand.” - Richard Feynman
This is a very famous and popular quote, but there are various ways of interpreting it, perhaps the most common interpretation could be paraphrased as, “what I cannot explain to a layperson and a curious child, I do not understand.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>